Part Three: Side Effects of
Pain Medications and Conclusion
Different pain treatments
can have different side effects.
For example, Gabapentin
can cause sleepiness or nausea,
so we recommend taking the medication
at night before bedtime.
We can change the dosing so
there is a good balance of effectiveness
in treating your nerve pain
and minimizing side effects.
Opioids can cause constipation.
For this,
we start everyone on a stool softener
like Docusate also known as Colace.
When they start to take the opioid medication.
Colace works by increasing the amount
of water the stool absorbs from the gut,
making the stool
softer and easier to pass.
You can often see relief in 1 to 3 days
when starting this medication.
If needed, we can add other medicines
like Miralax or Senna to help.
Miralax also increases
the water content in your stool
making it easier to pass to ease
bowel movements.
Senna on the other hand, works
by increasing the activity
of your intestines,
stimulating the muscles that line
the gut to help push stool along the bowel
and prompt a bowel movement.
Opioid Overdose Symptoms and Safety
It is important to be aware
of the symptoms of an opioid overdose,
which can include drowsiness,
extreme sleepiness, and trouble breathing.
We give everyone
a nasal spray called naloxone
to use in an emergency
in case of an overdose.
Remember, don't operate heavy machinery
or do anything dangerous
after taking the opioid medication.
And please have someone drive you to
and from radiation treatments.
We're here for you.
Going through radiotherapy can be tough,
but remember
we are here to help you manage your pain.
Don't
be afraid to tell us how you're feeling,
and we'll work together
to make you as comfortable as possible.
Please reach out to your doctors or nurses
with any questions
you may have along the way.
Thank you for watching.